<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The ouerthrovv of the most part of the Prince of Parma his forces, both horse and foote Performed on the twelfth and fifteenth of Iuly last, by the Graue Maurice his excellencie, generall of the armies in the lovve countries. With the breaking of the huge bridge leading to the Valew, neere Arnham. Seene and allowed.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1591</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 13 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16421</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 334</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117995</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853204</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853204</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18573</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16421)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18573)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 906:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The ouerthrovv of the most part of the Prince of Parma his forces, both horse and foote Performed on the twelfth and fifteenth of Iuly last, by the Graue Maurice his excellencie, generall of the armies in the lovve countries. With the breaking of the huge bridge leading to the Valew, neere Arnham. Seene and allowed.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T[homas] S[carlet, i.e. John Wolfe?] and are to be sold [by T. Nelson] ouer against the South doore of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1591.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The title-page woodcut was used by John Wolfe.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>The first and last leaves are blank.</note>
                  <note>Printer's and publisher's names from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Alessandro Farnese, --  Duke of Parma, 1545-1592 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Maurice, --  Prince of Orange, 1567-1625 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Netherlands --  History --  Wars of Independence, 1556-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18573:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18573:1"/>
            <p>THE Ouerthrovv of the moſt part of the Prince of <hi>Parma his forces, both horſe and foote.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Performed on the twelfth and fifteenth of Iuly laſt, by the Graue Maurice his Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie, Generall of the Armies in the Lowe Countries.</p>
            <p>With the breaking of the huge bridge leading to the Valew, neere Arnham.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seene and allowed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Printed by T.S. and are to be ſold ouer againſt the South doore of Pauls.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1591.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:18573:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18573:2"/>
            <head>A Letter written in Arnham by a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman of account on the ſixteenth of Iuly, concerning the great ouerthrow which the Prince of Parma lately ſustained.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He honourable ſerui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, aſſaultes and battels, lately made by his excellency vppon ſundry Townes in the Lowe Countries, together with the good ſucceſſe which hee hath had therein, hath of late giuen a great feare &amp; terrour to all the Towns neere there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>about, who although ſome of them doe ſtill ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bornly reſiſt &amp; withſtand his forces, hazarding their liues in the defence of the moſt capitall enemie vnto all true profeſſors of Chriſtian religion: yet the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expected victories which it hath pleaſed God to giue him of late, hath ſo daunted the moſt parte of thoſe, who-doe ſtill wilfully reſiſt him, as they did his excellencies Father, namely, the wiſe and valiaunt Prince of Orange, that the chiefeſt of them knowe not well what to do, nor which way to turne them.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:18573:3"/>
            <p>Wonderful hath bene his ſucceſſe ſince he tooke the cauſe of his country in hande, yea he hath daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the enemie more within the ſpace of one yeare, then was done by any other in ſeauen yeares before. How many Townes hath he lately obtained, wherein the enemie hath not made triall of his valour Nay, what Towne or Cittie in all the Low Countries that doth forcibly reſiſt the ſtates, which with an vndaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted courage he doth not attempt to conquere? Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly there is none that hee can eaſily come at, but hee ſeeketh meanes to compaſſe and countermaund the ſame, either by the Cannon or Cutlaſſe.</p>
            <p>For proofe wherof looke into his politike attempt lately made at Bredau, a thing moſt worthie of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie, where vnder the colour of bringing in Turfes to ſerue the Towne with ſome kinde of fuell (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of then they were in great want) he brought into the harbour hoyes laden with Turfes on the toppe, and armed men vnderneath, who in the dead time of the night, came forth and ſurprized the Towne.</p>
            <p>Call to minde his forwardnes at Graue ſconce Zurphen, Deuenter, Delftes Ile, and ſundry other Townes, whole honourable ſeruice, prowes, and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour performed at the ſame, maketh truth to ſpreade foorth his rare renowne into all Chriſtian nations, in ſo much as euerie one ſaith, his deedes deſerue to be chronicled, and his inuincible courage to bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtred in letters of gold.</p>
            <p>The Lorde of hoſtes hath aſſiſted him, yea hath preſerued him, as the apple of his eie, euen as hee did
<pb facs="tcp:18573:3"/>defend Dauid from the handes of the mightie Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of the Philiſtines: And although his excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies power at the firſt was but very weake, and then the enemies armie verie ſtrong, yet hath almightie God nowe greatly increaſed his power, and in moſt wonderful ſort pulled downe and weakened the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the ſaid Capitall enemie, yea, and that in ſuch ſort, as the ſame may ſeeme moſt wonderfull and ſtraunge to thoſe that enter into the due conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof.</p>
            <p>This Capitall enemie of whom I make recitall, is the Prince of Parma, who, although hee were (not long ſince) ſortie thouſand ſtrong, he is now greatly weakened, and his forces not aboue eight thouſand ſighting men in the field. The reaſon is, becauſe ſome of his chiefeſt Townes are reuolted, and his greateſt ſtrength of horſes and horſemen lately by Gods prouidence ſcattered, ſlaine, and taken priſoners, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides ſundry of his footmen maymed, diſcomfited, &amp; put to the ſword, as appeareth by this hiſtorie parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly enſuing.</p>
            <p>The Prince of Parma for truth, lying at Huffen, a Towneſcituate betweene Nimweghen and Arnham, after that hee perceiued his ſtrength was impaired, by reaſon of the Townes of Deuenter and Zutphen, which haue lately yeelded by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint, muſtered vp his men, hauing in all about ten thobſand ſoldiers, namely, two thouſand horſe, and eight thouſand foote, of which power, the greater
<pb facs="tcp:18573:4"/>part came and lay before Knotſenburgh ſconce, a fort builded verie ſtrong, and holden by the Graue Maurice his excellencie. This his armie hath made two ſeuerall aſſaults vpon the ſaid fort or ſconce, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerth eleſſe he hath beene repulſed to his great hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derance &amp; loſſe, for in the firſt aſſault the ſaid Prince of Parma hath loſt about ſix hundred men, &amp; twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſeuerall Captaines, the principall wherof was the Countie Octauio de Manfuelt, with Lamberlot his Lieutenant, and an Italian Prince. Beſides thoſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid which were ſlaine, there was alſo about the number of foure hundred more, who beeing ſore hurt, wcre carried into Nimweghen. This was vpon Monday beeing the 12 day of Iuly laſt paſt after our Engliſh computation: in which fight they ſeemed on both ſides verie hardie and couragious.</p>
            <p>And whereas the Prince of Parma had compac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a great and mightie bridge made of Lighters, ſir poles, and great planks, which reached ouer the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer of Rhine, into an Iland called Valew, the ſame beeiug chained together, was of ſuch breadth and ſtrength, that the Princcs armies, and troupes of ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med men did eaſily march and paſſe ouer it, when &amp; ſo often as they pleaſed. The like bridge hee had alſo made from the wall by Nimweghen, ouer to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wal or land ſide, leading toward Arnham, both which bridges are fortified with ſconces at the end, ſo that there was no eaſie way to come vnto them: betweene which lieth that Towne of Huſſen, where the Prince of Parma remained, thinking himſelfe
<pb facs="tcp:18573:4"/>there in greateſt ſafetie. But the Graue Maurice per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing that the bridge leading into the Valew was a great hinderance to his purpoſe, for paſſing vp the riuer before Nimweghen, polititikely and ſecretlie ſet forth a great many veſſels togither called Drum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medaries, which being well manned, came early in the morning forceably with Sea and Tide, and beate vppon the bridge with great labour, for the ſpace of foure howers together, in which time they had broken, cut, and ſawed the ſame in ſunder: this done, the force of the ſea tore the reſt of the bridge in pieces: by meanes whereof the Graue Maurice hath now free paſſage with his forces to paſſe vp to Nimweghen by the riuer, ſo that the Prince of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma finding his holde weakened, was conſtrained to flie to Nimweghen, where ſince his comming hee hath taken from them al their armour, and weapons of defence and deliuered the ſame into the cuſtodie of his owne ſoldiours, who are ioyned in equallitie with the principall ſurueiors and gouernors of that Cittie. The Princes armie and the Graue Maurices, do now lie within three Engliſh miles one of an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and it is ſuppoſed that their armies haue mette and fought together before this time, whereof you ſhall haue certaine intelligence by the next Poſt.</p>
            <p>After that his excellencie had receiued this good ſucceſſe ouer his enemies, hee with his forces gaue thankes vnto Almighty God, which done, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed themſelues, and reſted without dooing anie thing vntill the Thurſday morning following.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:18573:5"/>
            <p>Vpon which day, his excellencies forces hauing intelligence by ſome ſcoutes appertaining to their army, that the Prince of Parmas tenne Coronets of horſemen were at hand, yet ſecretly ambuſht, vntill ſome troupes of footmen ſhould haue come vp to them, prepared themſelues to fight, ſetting them ſelues in battell ray, and ſo marched forwards.</p>
            <p>The Prince of Parma, by reaſon he ſaw the Graue Maurice his company growe &amp; increaſe ſtil in grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter multitude, was reſolued to bid his excellencie battell, thinking that if he ſhould not do it, his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er would in ſhort ſpace grow mightier than his, yet not meaning to aduertiſe him thereof, but what hee did ſhould be on the ſuddaine, to the ende he might take the greater aduauntage of his excellencie, and to that end he prepared theſe Cornets of horſemen, who being placed in an ambuſh, was commaunded to keepe ſilence, and not beſeene vntill the footmen were come vnto them, which were preparing with all ſpeed, at what time theſe horſemen ſhould ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly haue come vpon the forces of the Graue Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice, and in a moment to haue wrought the ſpoile &amp; ouerthrow of them all. But of this politike pretence he was meerely defeated, for his excellencie hauing perfect knowledge of their ſtrength, and place of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bode, did forth with ſet vpon them in moſt couragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſort, which was at Betue, and there like ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous and moſt hardy ſoldiers, within foure howers ſpace did obtaine a moſt happy and famous victory ouer them. Of which tenne Coronets of horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,
<pb facs="tcp:18573:5"/>ſeuen companies were ſlaine and taken priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners forthwith.</p>
            <p>The firſt company of theſe horſemen ſo taken &amp; ſlaine, was Don Pedro Franciſco de Nicello, Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of the Guard to the Prince of Parma, hee was chiefe Generall ouer all theſe companies of horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, in the abſence of the Marques del Guaſto: al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo his Coronet, and Sir Tarquinio Geapido, being a Gentleman of a great houſe, was taken.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond company or Coronet of horſemen was Conto de Fio de Mantere, Lieutenant of Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Ieronimo Caraffa.</p>
            <p>In the third company or Cornet, was Captaine Paradilla, being grieuouſly hurt with three wounds, whereof hee died the next day, yet offered for his ranſome before his death, fifteen thouſand crowns.</p>
            <p>In the fourth company or Coronet was taken don de Aualos Altiueſo, brother to the Marques del Guaſto, who offereth for his raunſome thirtie thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Duckats: his Coronet was alſo taken.</p>
            <p>In the fift company was taken Don Antonio le Iaio with ſundry Gentlemen of account.</p>
            <p>In the ſixt company or Coronet was taken Bia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gio Cappizucca with ſundry other Gentlemen.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:18573:6"/>
            <p>In the ſeuenth Coronet was no men of name, they were all common Rutters, yet all taken priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</p>
            <p>Of theſe aforeſaid companies or Coronets of horſemen, there was foure hundred and odde hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes taken aliue, who were all by his excellencies for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces conducted and brought into the towne of Arn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, on the day aforeſaid, who were all taken at Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue.</p>
            <p>Beſides the taking of all theſe Captaines, Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets, and horſemen, the enemies bloudy auncient was taken, which remaineth in the ſaide Towne of Arnham.</p>
            <p>Graue Maurice his excellencie, in all theſe two aſſaults, hath not loſt aboue twentie men, being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſoldier, and no one man of name or account a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them.</p>
            <p>His excellencies forces is at this preſent fifteene hundred horſe, and ten thouſand footmen. He lyeth in the field ready to giue the enemie battell euery houre. As for the Prince of Parma he commeth not into the field, but keepeth himſelfe cloſe for feare of daunger that might thereby inſue vnto his perſon.</p>
            <p>It was a great incouragement and comfort vnto all the common ſoldiers, to ſee his excellencie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually in the field all the time of the battell, who promiſed vnto them all, that they ſhould not goe one foote further than he would hazard his owne perſon.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:18573:6"/>
            <p>Beſides thoſe ſeuen Coronets of horſemen before recited, there was foure Coronets all Rutters more, which they followed in chaſe, of whoſe ſucceſſe I haue not as yet receiued the particulars, but it is likely that they are taken, for that the paſſages were laid round about.</p>
            <p>Thus I ceaſe to write any more of his excellencie till further occaſion, whom I beſeech God to proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per with all his Army, and to graunt him victory, that he may ouerthrow the enemies of Gods truth, and build vp the decaied Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the land of Iſrael, which he graunt for his mercie ſake. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
